lan CramerSenior Front End Engineer

330.241.1957 iancramer55@gmail.com Cleveland, Ohio www.therealiancramer.com

Summary

I am a self starter with more than 13 years of experience as a front end engineer and designer. I lead development of public facing single page applications using the most current frameworks and best practices. I am user focused with the ability to make complex data more consumable in a frictionless workflow.

Technical Skills

TypeScript React JavaScript Next.js **HTML** CSS/SASS UX **NPM Styled Components REST API Functional Programming** Micro Front Ends GraphQL **Figma Design Systems Data Visualization** Performance Optimization Accessibility

Experience

Zillow Group - Senior Software Engineer

April 2022 - present

- Play a lead front end engineer role on the social impact team
- Lead front end engineering and design on several high impact projects including a feature to allow renters to report on time payments to the credit beureus
- Guide all engineers on my team in front end best practices in order to raise the quality of code produced, reduce tech debt, and maximize scalability.
- **Lowe's Companies** Senior Front End Engineer

August 2020 - March 2022

- Play a vital and influential role on development of new features for the public facing ecommerce web application having a direct impact on company sales
- Use the latest front end technologies including React, Micro Front Ends, and Typescript
- · Mentor junior engineers on best practices and approaches to front end engineering
- Work directly with PMs, designers, and back end teams to coordinate and plan features
- Lead discussions on architecture decisions and overall direction of the front end teams
- FireEye, Inc. Senior Front End Engineer

July 2017 - February 2020

- Led team of engineers to develop and deliver design system component library used by engineers company wide and implemented in public facing products in React and Angular
- Managed, published, and versioned component libraries as Node packages
- Fostered collaborative environment between engineering contributors company wide to treat the component library as an "open source" project within the company
- Conducted code reviews for all GitHub pull requests
- Facilitated communication between designers and engineers
- Single handedly deigned and built very successful front end of application for analyzing machine learning models with heavy data visualization
- Guided threat analysis product team to use better JavaScript practices to improve performance and user experience

Kalibrate - Senior Front End Engineer

October 2016 - July 2017

- Sole front end engineer in developing a brand new wholesale fuel pricing application
- Designed and engineered a user interface that dynamically builds itself at run time using user defined meta-data retrieved from an API including CRUD operations and navigation elements

DecisionDesk - Lead Front End Engineer

May 2016 - October 2016

- Helped this start-up company in the last few months of its existence to breath life into their product in time for the upcoming college enrollment season
- Lead effort to improve performance and usability while creating more stable product

Medical Mutual - Front End Engineer

April 2015 - May 2016

As part of the user experience team as a front end developer I contributed to several projects in the company. My main responsibility was generating HTML/CSS/JS for the Uls. I collaborated with server side developers in a C#.NET MVC environment to create dynamic content and integrate code from the Ul's into Sitecore.

The majority of my time was spent on the online enrollment application for the Medical Mutual Individual Insurance Marketplace and the My Health Plan application where existing members manage their insurance plan.

Macy's - Front End Engineer

October 2014 - April 2015

Brought in as a contractor 2 months into the project, I was a part of building a new CRM system for Macy's and Bloomingdale's department stores. As the front end developer I was in charge of coding the Javascript, HTML, and CSS for the user interface.

I lead the way to better front end practices in order to create a more sustainable, lean code base. I introduced the team to responsive design in order to make a code base that is not only re-usable across brands, but across devices as well.

Avantia, Inc - Front End Engineer / Designer

January 2013 - October 2014

I designed and developed user interfaces and user experiences for client projects while collaborating with several different development teams. At any given time I was juggling multiple projects.

My most notable work was on the ongoing development of the Ben and Jerry's website to integrate it into the content management system Jahia. I also did work for clients such as Lands' End and Cleveland Clinic.

AmTrust - Front End Engineer / Designer

March 2012 - January 2013

 Re-designed the company's web applications implementing a cohesive, company-wide style, while setting up a seamless transition from one style sheet to the next without disrupting current functionality.

Education

Baldwin-Wallace University - Bachelor's Degree **Areas of Study** - Art/Computer Science

2006 - 2010